Okay, today's דף Daf is מ"ח, Mem Chet, גיטין Gittin 48. We
pick up nine lines from the bottom on מ"ז עמוד ב, Mem
Zayin Amud Bet, איתיבי, eitvei, second word in the line. And we
are in the middle of a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, where the משנה Mishnah spoke about ביכורים
Bikkurim and about when you sell a field to a non-Jew, what
that does that do to the status of the fruit regarding ביכורים.
Bikkurim. And that the גמרא Gemara then moved on from that to
a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
if somebody sells a field לפירות, le-peirot, you own the ground not
to
actually actual title in the land and to make actual changes in
the land, but you own it for the right of the fruit
that grows with it. Is that ownership of the land for the
sake of its fruit, is that would that entitle you to be
מביא וקורא? mevi ve-korei? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you can bring
the ביכורים, Bikkurim, you have they're your fruit, you can bring them
and you can say האדמה אשר נתתה לי, ha-adamah asher natata li,
the land is enough yours at least vis-à-vis you have enough ownership
and title to the land to say האדמה אשר נתתה לי. ha-adamah
asher natata li. And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no, you bring
because they're fruit of yours, but you cannot say האדמה אשר נתתה
לי, ha-adamah asher natata li, אינו קורא. eino korei. And the גמרא
Gemara explains that according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish קנין פירות לאו
כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peirot lav ke-kinyan haguf dami. The owning of
the land for the fruit is not like the actual owning of
the land. And now the גמרא Gemara is in the middle of
bringing proofs for either side. So nine lines from the bottom, איתיבי,
eitvei, I'll ask a question. We have a ברייתא: Beraisa: היה בדרך,
haya ba-derech, a man is going on the way, וביכורי אשתו בידו,
u-vikkurei ishto beyado, and he's bringing fruit from his wife's property. This
is נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, she owns the his wife owns the
title and he has owns the fruit. So he has the ownership
of the land for the sake of the fruit, exactly our case.
ושמע שמתה אשתו, ve-shama she-meisah ishto, and then he heard that his
wife died. So now before he had a chance to actually deliver
the fruit, he now has now taken title of the land, let's
see because he inherits from his wife. מביא וקורא, mevi ve-korei, he
brings and he recites the פסוק pasuk on the land that you
have given me. So the גמרא Gemara makes the obvious inference: מתה
אין לא מתה לא. meisah in lo meisah lo. It sounds like
he only says this because his wife died and now he can
say האדמה אשר נתתה לי, ha-adamah asher natata li, but without that
he would not be able to say האדמה אשר נתתה לי, ha-adamah
asher natata li, which proves like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that you
can if you have the field לפירות le-peirot you can be מביא
mevi but you are אינו קורא. eino korei. You cannot say it,
קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peirot lav ke-kinyan haguf dami.
So the גמרא Gemara says: לא, lo, no, according to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan I would reject that inference. I would say הוא הדין
אף על גב דלא מתה, hu hadin af al gav de-lo meisah,
even if his wife didn't die he could say האדמה אשר נתתה
לי. ha-adamah asher natata li. Certainly doesn't sound that way, but ומתה
איצטריכי, u-meisah itzterichei, there's a חידוש chidush that even when his wife
dies he's still allowed to say. Now what's the חידוש? chidush? He's
even more his land. But the חידוש chidush is that now he
has a new relationship to the fruit, it's like some status change
occurred in the middle. And even though beforehand he could say האדמה
אשר נתתה לי, ha-adamah asher natata li, he could be מביא וקורא
mevi ve-korei and now he could say it, because there's some status
change in the middle, even though the status change should seem relatively
trivial in this case, since it doesn't affect the ביכורים, Bikkurim, nevertheless
that might be a reason to not allow him to say it.
Why? Because of ליגזרו משום דרבי יוסי בר חנינא, ligzeiru mishum de-Rabbi
Yose ben Chanina, because it looks too similar to the case of
רבי יוסי בר חנינא. Rabbi Yose ben Chanina. דאמר רבי יוסי בר
חנינא, de-amar Rabbi Yose ben Chanina, בצרן ושגרן ביד שליח, bitzan ve-shigan
beyad shaliach, if the owner harvests the fruit and then sends them
through a שליח, shaliach, ומת שליח בדרך u-meit shaliach baderech and the
שליח shaliach dies on the way, מביא ואינו קורא, mevi ve-eino korei,
and then the and then the owner goes ahead and he picks
up the fruit, the שליח shaliach died at a
hotel halfway along the way in Haifa and he goes ahead and
he picks them up at the hotel in Haifa and continues bringing
them to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. In that case he is not able to
say the פסוק. pasuk. Why?
Because
שנאמר ולקחת והבאת, shene'emar ve-lakachta ve-heiveta, you shall take and you shall
bring, עד שתהא לקיחה והבאה באחד ad she-tehei lekichah ve-hava'ah be-echad קמשמע
לן. kemashma lan. The לקיחה lekichah and the bringing should all be
done by one person, and here there was a שליח shaliach in
the middle. He the owner did the harvesting, there's a question in
תוספות Tosafos is that considered the לקיחה, lekichah, maybe that is. And
then the שליח shaliach did part of the bringing and then the
owner finished the bringing, and that interruption there, or maybe it's because
the שליח shaliach is considered to have done the initial taking out
of the house and that's the לקיחה, lekichah, but the fact that
there were two statuses, that is enough to prevent the owner from
saying האדמה ha-adamah from doing the קריאה. keriah. Now and that is
a question, how really similar is that to our case? In that
case when the שליח shaliach himself was going to bring it, the
שליח shaliach could not say the הלכה halachah is a שליח shaliach
does not do the קריאה, keriah, it's not at the end of
the day the שליח's shaliach property. So there's a real change in
status there, meaningful change in status vis-à-vis
the statement of האדמה אשר נתתה לי. ha-adamah asher natata li. Here
of course there's nothing like that because according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan the husband
could have did מביא וקורא mevi ve-korei even before his wife died.
Nevertheless the גמרא's Gemara saying that's how רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would
read this ברייתא. Beraisa. Of course he could have brought it before,
but after his wife died you might have think that that makes
it like a separate status and maybe it's too similar to this
case and telling you even so he can go ahead and read
it. Okay. Certainly not worthy evidence. with a simple reading of that
ברייתא braita *beraita*. Okay, קא משמע לן *kamashma lan*. ואזלו לטעמייהו *ve'azlu
letamaihu*. Now this debate of יוחנן *Yochanan* and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
*Resh Lakish* follows their debate elsewhere where, where they, you know,
discuss the following. דאיתמר *de'itmar* was taught: המוכר שדהו בזמן שהיובל נוהג
*hamocher sadeh bizman shehayovel noheg*, rather than framing it in the context
of selling a field for the פירות Peros *peirot*, they frame it
in the context of selling a field when the יובל Yovel *Yovel*
is in place. And when the יובל Yovel *Yovel* is in place,
you know, any field that you sell ultimately will revert back to
you when the יובל Yovel *Yovel* comes around. So therefore any ownership
that anyone has over it, it's only for a temporary period of
time. Okay. Now, so is that considered sufficient ownership, that time-bound ownership?
יוחנן אומר מביא וקורא meivi ve'korei *Yochanan omer meivi vekorei*, you can
bring it and say האדמה אשר נתת לי *ha'adamah asher natata li*.
וריש לקיש אומר מביא ואינו קורא meivi v'eino korei, *VeResh Lakish omer
meivi ve'eino korei*, you cannot say it, it's time-bound so you don't
really have permanent title to the land. Now, יוחנן אומר מביא וקורא
meivi ve'korei קנין פירות כקנין הגוף kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf. דמי *Yochanan
omer meivi vekorei kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf dami*. Now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* here ties this to this קנין פירות kinyan peiros. *kinyan peirot*
debate, but as it will say in a minute, this seems to
be even more than קנין פירות kinyan peirot *kinyan peirot*. יוחנן *Yochanan*
says even though you only have rights to the fruit because you
don't have total title to the land, so since your title to
the land is time-bound, it's like you really only have full ownership
over the fruit. Nevertheless, that's considered like full ownership over the land,
קנין פירות כקנין הגוף *kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf*, and you can be
מביא וקורא meivi ve'korei *meivi vekorei*. וריש לקיש אומר מביא ואינו קורא
meivi ve'eino korei קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי *VeResh Lakish omer
meivi ve'eino korei kinyan peirot lav kekinyan haguf dami*. No, it's only
temporary and therefore you don't really own the land, and even though
you own the fruit, that doesn't- it's not as if you own
the land, and therefore you cannot be קורא korei *korei*, you cannot
say האדמה אשר נתת לי *ha'adamah asher natata li*. Now clearly this
case should give you much greater, you know, is a much stronger
reason to say that you can say האדמה אשר נתת לי *ha'adamah
asher natata li*. I mean, maybe you can't because the idea of
ביכורים bikurim *Bikkurim* is the sense of, you know, your ultimate inheritance
and, and therefore it's the land that is your שדה אחוזה sade
achuza? *sedei achuzah*, that might be a claim. But the fundamental question
of are you considered to be the owner, if the land was
sold to you and it was sold without any qualifications, even though
that there is a system that is going to make the land
revert, but fundamentally now you own the land, you know, and you
would think that there should be no limitations on what you can
do to the land. Number one. Number two is even if it
was explicitly said "I'm selling you the land for ten years", it
wasn't like some external system kicked in, still, since it's framed as
selling the land, you would think that that's a much stronger reason
to say that you're considered like you own the land and can
be מביא וקורא meivi ve'korei *meivi vekorei*. So there's a much greater
reason why in the case of יובל Yovel *Yovel* rather than selling
it just for the fruit that one would be inclined to go
like יוחנן *Yochanan*. And the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* basically says this: וצריכא
*utzricha*, you need to tell me both cases. דאי איתמר בהא *de'i
itmar beha*, if you had just told me in the case
of
explicitly selling it just for the fruit, בהא קאמר ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish *beha ka'amar Resh Lakish*—דכי נחית אדעתא דפירי נחית *dechi nachit ada'ata
depeiri nachit*—in that case ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Resh Lakish* says okay,
from the very beginning your whole relationship to the land was just
your ownership for the sake of rights to the fruit. אבל בהא
*aval beha*, but in this case of selling the entire property, it
just happens to be that it's in a time when the יובל
Yovel, *Yovel* takes effect, דאדעתא דגופא נחית *da'ada'ata degufa nachit*, you are-
you want to purchase it, your sense is I'm buying the whole
land, right? It might be that eventually it'll revert, but your relationship
to it is to take full possession of the land. So therefore
אימא מודי ליה ליוחנן *eima modi leh leYochanan*, maybe he would agree
to יוחנן *Yochanan* that that does give you a real sense of
ownership and title. ואי איתמר בהא *ve'i itmar beha*, if you had
just said this case by יובל Yovel *Yovel*, בהא קאמר יוחנן *beha
ka'amar Yochanan*, that's where יוחנן *Yochanan* says you have a real title
for the reason we just said, because you said you were acquiring
the land. אבל בהא *aval beha*, but when from the very outset
you say you're only taking possession of it for the sake of
the fruit, אימא מודי ליה לריש לקיש *eima modi leh leResh Lakish*,
צריכא *tzricha*. I might think he agrees to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
*Resh Lakish*, so therefore it has to tell you that even in
that case. So יוחנן *Yochanan* is so ready to call- consider you
to be the owner of the land and say האדמה אשר נתת
לי *ha'adamah asher natata li* even if you just own land for
the sake of the fruit. וריש לקיש *VeResh Lakish* has such a
high bar that even when the יובל Yovel *Yovel* is נוהג *noheg*,
even though you bought the land to own it fully, for the-
because the יובל Yovel *Yovel* is נוהג *noheg*, you are not full
owner of the land and you cannot say האדמה אשר נתת לי
*ha'adamah asher natata li*. Okay. צריכא. תא שמע *Tzricha. Ta shema*. Come
and hear. הקונה אילן וקרקעו *Hakoneh ilan vekarkao*, מביא וקורא meivi ve'korei,
*meivi vekorei*. If you buy the land- if you buy a tree
and the land underneath it, you can go ahead and say האדמה
אשר נתת לי *ha'adamah asher natata li*. So presumably, right, this is,
you know, you're purchasing it, it's not your ancestral land. And presumably
we're talking that the יובל Yovel. *Yovel* is being נוהג *noheg*. I
don't know why we're assuming that, since that basically stopped in the
first בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, but that's at least the
initial assumption of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. And therefore you see that
even when the יובל Yovel *Yovel* applies, you can be מביא וקורא
*meivi vekorei*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no: הכא במאי עסקינן
בזמן שאין היובל נוהג *hacha bemai askinan bizman she'ein hayovel noheg*. We're
talking that the יובל Yovel *Yovel* no longer applies, which was towards
the end of the בית ראשון *Bayis Rishon* period where you did
not have the twelve tribes all on their land. תא שמע *Ta
shema*... תא שמע come and hear. הקונה שני אילנות בתוך שדה חברו,
Hakoneh shnei ilanos besoch seday chavero, if you buy two trees without
specifying the land underneath, מביא ואינו קורא, then you do not—you bring
ביכורים bikurim. but you're not קורא because two trees do not give
you the land. השלושה, Hashlosha, but if you buy three trees, the
גמרא Gemara comments, then as we say elsewhere when you buy three
trees, you know, and they sort of make a triangle, they're presumed
to include the land between them. So in that case מביא וקורא
because you bought the land, you can bring. So הכא נמי בזמן
שאין יובל נוהג, hacha nami bizman she'ein Yovel noheg, that doesn't prove
anything. Of course there're going to be cases in the משנה Mishna
that when you purchase it you're מביא וקורא because the משנה Mishna
is talking about times when the יובל Yovel. does not apply. So
it's going to be pretty hard to count—to bring a counter-proof. Okay,
והא דאמר
רב חסדא,
veha d'amar
Rav Chisda, מחלוקת ביובל שני, machlokes b'Yovel sheni, אבל ביובל ראשון, aval
b'Yovel rishon, דברי הכל מביא וקורא. divrei hakol meivi ve'korei. And now
said the גמרא, Gemara רב חסדא Rav Chisda actually has an interesting
teaching. He says that even רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that considers this
to be a non-full ownership of the land would only say it
after the first יובל Yovel was practiced in the land of ישראל.
Yisrael. But in the time of, you know, way back in the
time of יהושע Yehoshua and the שופטים Shoftim when the יובל Yovel
was—before the first יובל Yovel was—very, very first one was practiced, at
that point everybody would agree that it would be considered to be
a קנין הגוף. kinyan haguf. Why is it different? He says ביובל
ראשון דברי הכל מביא וקורא דאכתי לא סמכא דעתייהו. b'Yovel rishon divrei
hakol meivi ve'korei d'achti lo samcha da'atayhu. Because people, both the owner
and the buyer and the seller aren't really feel so confident about
that the land is going to go back, you know, they heard
there's this idea in the תורה Torah called יובל, Yovel, but it's
never been practiced, who knows if people are going to enforce it,
who knows how it's really going to play out in practice, and
therefore in people's minds they're thinking that the sale might really wind
up to be final. And therefore interestingly, you know, even though according
to on the books the sale is not final, on the books
the יובל Yovel is going to be put into effect, since their
relationship to it is as if it's final, that's enough to give
the purchaser a sense of a קנין הגוף. kinyan haguf. Now it
is true that, you know, ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish statement that when
the יובל Yovel takes place it's not a קנין הגוף kinyan haguf
is a pretty high bar. I mean, right? You intended to buy
the land, you do own it, it's just that it will reverse.
So maybe that's why the question of intent is enough to change,
you know, perception is enough to change that הלכה. halacha. Because legally
you own it, it's just legally some mechanism is going to come
and it's going to make it revert back. And therefore what makes
your ownership not complete is not that legally you don't own it
fully, but that you know and your relationship to it is different
because you know you will not have full rights to it. And
therefore when that perception is different the הלכה halacha will change. Otherwise
it's quite strange why your perception should change the actual way הלכה
halacha assesses what is your legal relationship to this land. But you
know it sort of really does prove a principle that I've sort
of really have learned as a head of a rabbinical school which
is said by some educators as like, you know, culture eats curriculum
for lunch, which basically means it doesn't matter what the rules are
on the books. What matters is, you know, the culture and what
is being messaged implicitly or explicitly in terms of what are the
real rules that govern the place, and that much more shapes people's
sense of what their responsibilities are and you know and what the
demands are. So anyway, so that's what רב חסדא Rav Chisda said.
So now that we've said that even ריש לקיש Resh Lakish before
the first יובל Yovel kicked in would agree that it would be
considered to be a קנין הגוף kinyan haguf because of people's perception,
that could be the answer to any evidence that seems to say
מביא וקורא during the יובל. Yovel That we would be talking before
the
יובל ראשון. Yovel rishon. Okay.
לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא ביובל ראשון הא ביובל שני. ha b'Yovel
rishon ha b'Yovel sheni. That when anything that says that during the
time of the יובל yovel or anything that might be talking about
the יובל yovel. that says that you're מביא וקורא would be before
the יובל ראשון Yovel rishon and ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish. statement that
you're מביא ואינו קורא would be before—would be after the יובל שני.
Yovel sheni. Okay. לימא כתנאי, Leima k'tannai,
let's say that this debate of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש parallels a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Now it's worth noting that
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש only spoke vis-à-vis the יובל.
yovel. It is the גמרא Gemara that framed it—excuse me, vis-à-vis ביכורים.
Bikkurim. It is the גמרא Gemara that framed it in general terms
of קנין פירות כקנין הגוף. And for all we know רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש were really talking about a narrow question
of the requirements of מביא וקורא, but because the גמרא Gemara has—and
not something that could be applied elsewhere in הלכה halacha in terms
of a general question of קנין פירות. But because the גמרא's gemara.
broader framing, it's going to try to connect it to other debates.
So let's take a look.
מנין ללוקח שדה מאביו והקדישה ואחר כך מת אביו מנין שתהא לפניו
כשדה אחוזה. Minyin le'loke'ach sade me'aviv ve'hikdisha ve'achar kach mes aviv minyin
she'tehei lefanav k'sade achuza. How do you know somebody who purchases a
field from his father and he sanctifies it and then his father
dies, okay, before the יובל yovel. kicks in, how do you know
that that's like a שדה אחוזה? Sdei Achuzah, What does this mean?
So if somebody
sanctifies... it belongs to the כהנים Kohanim but this person cannot sanctify
more than he owns. It belongs to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
rather, but you know and but so therefore even though the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash owns it starting as of now, when the יובל
yovel, comes, it'll go back to the original owner because the purchaser
cannot sanctify more than he owns. But if the person who owns
the land as an inheritance and the ancestral land sanctifies it, it's
a שדה אחוזה, Sdei Achuzah. then the תורה Torah says that when
the
יובל yovel, comes
it goes to the כהנים Kohanim and it does not go back
to the owner because the owner had full ownership and he sanctified
it. That's a שדה אחוזה. Sdei Achuzah, So here you have a
story about somebody who purchased a field from his father, a field
that he would inherit, he sanctified it before he inherited it, he
sanctified it when it was in his hands just as a purchased
field when it was something that would have gone back to his
father in the יובל, yovel, and then before the יובל hit, his
father died, and now he has total title to it, and now
the יובל comes along. What's the הלכה? halacha? Is the הלכה, halacha,
well since you have total title and you sanctified it so now
thank you very much the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is going to
keep it, or is it since when you sanctified it you didn't
yet have total title and you weren't able to sanctify the entirety
of it, so now the יובל comes it goes back to your
father, your father is dead and now you inherit it from your
father? So what's the הלכה? halacha?
So the ברייתא braita says it is like a שדה אחוזה, Sdei
Achuzah it is treated as if you sanctified it when it was
an ancestral land and it stays with the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash,
and with the כהנים. Kohanim. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אם משדה מקנתו
אשר לא משדה אחוזתו. im sdei miknaso asher lo mi-sdei achuzaso. If
you sanctify a field that you purchased which was not a field
of inheritance. It's a little redundant, just say if you sanctify a
field of inheritance it stays with the כהנים Kohanim and the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, so if it's a field that you purchased it
goes back to the owner. Why do you have to say if
it's a field that you purchased that's not a field of inheritance?
So what is the reason for that phrase? שדה שאינה ראויה להיות
שדה אחוזה, Sadeh she-einah re'uyah lihyot sdei achuzah, to tell you that
the only time that field goes back to the original owner is
if the field not only was a field you purchased but a
field that was not fit or like didn't have the potential and
then an actualized potential of becoming your ancestral land. It's completely removed
from the category of your ancestral land.
יצא זו שראויה להיות שדה אחוזה, Yatza zo she-re'uyah lihyot sdei achuzah,
דברי רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון, divrei Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon, which excludes
this case. This case it was fit to become a שדה אחוזה
Sdei Achuzah and not just fit but that actually actualized, right? If
the guy bought it from his father, sanctified it, his father is
still alive, it would go back to his father, but here in
this case this land that was purchased was both a purchased land
and it became a שדה אחוזה Sdei Achuzah. and it was in
that potential category, you know, from the very outset, and in that
case it is going to stay with the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash
okay, because ultimately you have title now and that means that the
בית המקדש is entitled to keep it. You are the one that
sanctified it. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
disagrees. מנין ללוקח שדה מאביו ומת אביו ואחר כך הקדישה? Minayin lelokeach
sadeh me'aviv u-met aviv v'achar kach hikdishah? No, no, no, if the
father dies and then you sanctify it, in that case, מנין שתהא
לפניו כשדה אחוזה? minayin she-tehei lefanav ke-sdei achuzah?
Then even though when you first got it it was a purchased
field, since by the time you got around to sanctifying it it
had become your ancestral land, in that case that has a status
of שדה אחוזה. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אם משדה מקנתו אשר לא
משדה אחוזתו. im sdei miknaso asher lo mi-sdei achuzaso. שדה שאינה שדה
אחוזה. Sadeh she-einah sdei achuzah.
So if when is it, when do you does it go back?
When at the moment you sanctified it it wasn't an ancestral land.
יצא זו שהיא שדה אחוזה. Yatza zo she-hi sdei achuzah. To exclude
this case where it was already an ancestral land when you sanctified
it. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say
it's enough that it had the potential to be an ancestral land
when you sanctified it if in the end that potential was actualized,
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it has to actually be an
ancestral land when you sanctified it
in order for it to not go back. Now what is this
debate? So you could just say the debate is about how to
read the פסוקים, pesukim, but the גמרא Gemara. wants to and notice
this is not a debate about ביכורים. But the גמרא Gemara. wants
to make this a debate about your relationship to the land, it
wants to make this a debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש, Rabbi
Yochanan and Resh Lakish, because clearly you're purchasing this when the יובל
is being practiced, that you have to say that, that's the whole
framework here. And therefore the initial purchase it was only a קנין
פירות because it would have gone back before the father died. So
the גמרא Gemara, says like this. ואילו
לרבי יהודה ורבי שמעון מת אביו
ואחר כך הקדישה לא צריכא קרא. V'ilu
le-Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon met aviv v'achar
kach hikdishah lo tzricha krah.
So for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon what
entitles them to interpret the verse that when it is a שדה
מקנה Sdei Miknah that's not even the potential... potential of being a
שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*? Why didn't they need to first learn the
חידוש *chiddush* of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*? That it is a, that
you know, that the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is saying that even though
it starts as a שדה מקנה *sdei mikna*, if it ends as
a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza* before you sanctify it, it's the status
of a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*. How did they take that for
granted and they were able to go immediately to the case of
even having the potential of being a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*? מאי
לאו בהא קמיפלגי *Mai lav be-ha kamiplagi*. So let's see how the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* spells this out. This must be what they debate.
בהא קמיפלגי *Be-ha kamiplagi*. דרבי מאיר סבר קניין פירות kinyan perot, כקניין
הגוף דמי *De-Rabbi Meir savar kinyan peiros ke-kinyan ha-guf dami*. רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* holds that קניין פירות *kinyan peiros* is like קניין הגוף
kinyan haguf, *kinyan ha-guf*. So as soon as this guy bought it
from his father, it was considered to be like he was the
real owner. ובהא במיתת אביו השתא... ובהא במיתת אביו הוא דלא ירית
ולא מידי *U-ve-ha be-misas aviv hu de-lo yaris ve-lo midi*. And therefore,
and therefore he was already considered to be the owner before his
father died. And again, this is קניין פירות *kinyan peiros* because it's
the time when the יובל *Yovel* is being practiced. So this guy
bought it from his father, if we assume that for רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי *kinyan peiros ke-kinyan ha-guf*, he's
already considered to be the full owner. Now his father died, I
might think that when the תורה Torah *Torah* has to assess, is
this a שדה מקנה *sdei mikna* or שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*, the
תורה Torah, *Torah* will say it's a שדה מקנה *sdei mikna* because
he was considered to be the full owner. And the fact that
now he also became a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*, maybe that doesn't
change his status according to in this question of what happens when
he sanctifies it. So therefore, let's take a look. ובהא במיתת אביו
השתא... במיתת אביו הוא דלא ירית ולא מידי *Be-misas aviv hu de-lo
yaris ve-lo midi*.
It's like he didn't inherit anything. Now obviously it is different because
even if he was like the full owner before his father died,
now he is the full owner and it's not going to reverse.
But okay, if he had that status as full owner before, then
maybe when his father dies and he gets it as an inheritance,
that doesn't change his status. הלכך *Hilkach*, and therefore, הוא דלא ירית
ולא מידי *hu de-lo yaris ve-lo midi*. הלכך מת אביו ואחר כך
הקדישה צריך קרא *Hilkach mes aviv ve-achar kach hikdisha tzarich kra*. And
therefore I need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to tell me that in
that case it's considered a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza* because I could
say the שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza* status does not take over the
שדה מקנה *sdei mikna* status because even at the שדה מקנה *sdei
mikna* level he was considered to be the full owner. Okay? So
why does רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* for
the case of the father dying before you sanctified it? That should
certainly be a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*. No, he needs a פסוק
Pasuk. *pasuk* because you were already considered the full owner even before
the father died. So you need the פסוק *pasuk* to tell me
that now that the father died it is going to supersede and
be considered a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*. So that shows קניין פירות
כקניין הגוף דמי *kinyan peiros ke-kinyan ha-guf*. ורבי יהודה ורבי שמעון סברי
קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף דמי kinyan perot lav kekinyan haguf dami
*Ve-Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon savri kinyan peiros lav ke-kinyan ha-guf dami*. They
will hold it's not like קניין הגוף kinyan haguf. *kinyan ha-guf*. והלכך
מת אביו ואחר כך הקדישה *Ve-hilkach mes aviv ve-achar kach hikdisha*. When
the guy bought it from his father and then the father died,
לא צריכה קרא *lo tzericha kra*. Of course that's a שדה אחוזה
*sdei achuza* because the father died before he sanctified it. First he
owned it as, was not considered the owner, only a קניין פירות
*kinyan peiros*. Then his father died, he inherited it, he was considered
the owner. So of course now that he comes to sanctify it,
it is considered to be a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*. So you
don't need a פסוק *pasuk* for that. וכי איצטריך קרא *Ve-chi itztarich
kra*, why do you need a פסוק *pasuk*? להקדישה ואחר כך מת
אביו *Le-hikdisha ve-achar kach mes aviv*. To tell me the case that
it was sanctified and then his father died. That case you would
really think that it would be a שדה מקנה *sdei mikna* and
the פסוק *pasuk* is telling you that no, it's still a שדה
אחוזה *sdei achuza* because it had that potential before he sanctified it
and that potential was actualized. Okay? במיתת אביו השתא הוא דקא ירית
*Be-misas aviv hashta hu de-ka yaris*. והלכך מת אביו ואחר כך הקדישה
לא צריכא קרא *Ve-hilkach mes aviv ve-achar kach hikdisha lo tzericha kra*.
וכי איצטריך קרא להקדישה ואחר כך מת אביו הוא דאיצטריך *Ve-chi itztarich
kra le-hikdisha ve-achar kach mes aviv hu de-itztarich*. Okay. So now we've
said that maybe that shows you that that's the debate. Okay, whether
they feel you need the פסוק *pasuk*, you can jump to the
more bigger חידוש *chiddush* of even when you sanctified it with the
potential, it's considered שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza* if that potential is actualized.
That you would be able to jump to that חידוש *chiddush* because
the other case would be obvious if you said קניין פירות לאו
כקניין הגוף דמי kinyan perot lav kekinyan haguf dami. *kinyan peiros lav
ke-kinyan ha-guf dami*. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק לעולם אימא לך בעלמא
קסברי רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי *Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak le-olam eima lach be-alma kasvari Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon
kinyan peiros ke-kinyan ha-guf dami*. I will tell you that רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* actually hold קניין פירות *kinyan
peiros* is like קניין הגוף *kinyan ha-guf*. And therefore and even they
hold like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. Okay. So if that's true, why
were they able to jump to the חידוש *chiddush* of potential? והכא
רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון קרא אשכחו ודרוש *Ve-hacha Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon
kra ashkechu ve-darush*. They found an extra twist in the פסוק *pasuk*
that let them do a double דרשה *derasha*. לכתוב רחמנא אם משדה
מקנתו אשר לא אחוזתו *Lichtov rachmana im mi-sdei miknaso asher lo achuzaso*.
It could have said, you know, it could have just said משדה
מקנתו *mi-sdei miknaso*. The fact that it says אשר לא משדה אחוזתו
*asher lo mi-sdei achuzaso*, that whole extra phrase allows you to learn
out one of these הלכות *halachos*. And what the גמרא *Gemara* is
now saying is that extra phrase is doubly extra because it could
have just said אשר לא אחוזתו *asher lo achuzaso*. מאי משדה אחוזתו
*Mai mi-sdei achuzaso*? Is that from the field of his אחוזה *achuza*?
שדה שאינה ראויה להיות שדה אחוזה *Sdeh she-einah re'uyah lihyos sdeh achuza*.
Something that doesn't even have the potential. It's משדה *mi-sdeh*, it's not
even like a derivative, it doesn't even have the potential of being
a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*. יצא זו שראויה להיות שדה אחוזה *Yatza
zu she-re'uyah lihyos sdeh achuza*. That excludes this that can be a
שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*. So
even
what, to say again... Guy bought it and then his father died.
So if קניין פירות *kinyan peirot* is כקניין הגוף *kekinyan haguf*, you
might think that since he, before his father died, he was already
considered to be the full owner, it does not change the state,
it's not now treated as שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*, so therefore the
פסוק *pasuk* teaches you it is treated as שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*.
That status supersedes and now when he sanctifies it, it's שדה אחוזה
*sdei achuza* because there's a double language of the פסוק *pasuk* משדה
אחוזתו *misedei achuzato*, we do that even one further and say that
even if he sanctified it before his father died and it really
wasn't שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza* at all, it just had the potential,
even in that case it's treated as a שדה אחוזה *sdei achuza*
if that potential actualizes and his father dies. Okay. Phew. Now, okay.
אמר רבי יוסף *Amar Rabbi Yosef*: אילו לאו דאמר רבי יוחנן קניין
פירות כקניין הגוף דמי *Ilu lav d'amar Rabbi Yochanan kinyan peiros kekinyan
haguf dami*, if it were not that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said
קניין פירות *kinyan peiros* is קניין הגוף *kinyan haguf*, לא מצא ידיו
ורגליו בבית המדרש *lo matza yadav v'raglav b'veis hamedrash*, he would not
find his hands and feet in the בית המדרש *beis hamedrash*, meaning
he couldn't even get started in learning. Why?
Because of another statement of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. דאמר רבי אסי
אמר רבי יוחנן האחים שחלקו לקוחות הן ומחזירין זה לזה ביובל *D'amar
Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachachim shechalku l'kuchos hein umachzirin zeh lazeh
b'yovel*. Let's say, you know, father dies and two brothers inherit the
estate and then they divide it up. You know, you take the
field in the north and I'll take the field in the south.
Halakhically how do we conceptualize that? Do we conceptualize that like, you
know, ראובן Reuven *Reuven* directly got the field in the north and
שמעון *Shimon* directly got the field in the south? Or do we
conceptualize it as ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and שמעון *Shimon* both got ownership
in both fields and therefore each had 50 percent of each? And
ראובן Reuven *Reuven* swapped his 50 percent in the south for שמעון
*Shimon*'s 50 percent in the north. Okay, that's the other way. So
the one of the ways that the גמרא *Gemara* sort of says
you can conceptualize this is the question of יש ברירה *yeish breira*
or not. When you divide something up, is it like retroactively we'll
say that's always the way it was meant to be? Maybe you
can know, you can apply that in many different scenarios. In the
case of inheritance, maybe you would specifically say that, you know, that
ultimately how they work it out, that makes it as if they
directly inherited those parts. But רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says no, we
don't look at it that way. We look at it as though
you actually each owned half and you sold your other half and
so on, and therefore לקוחות הן *lakuchos hein*, they are considered to
have purchased each other's half from the part that they wound up
with. So if that's true, so these two brothers inherit. Okay, they
divide it, one gets a field in the south, one gets a
field in the north. And it's when the יובל *yovel* is נוהג
*noheig*. So what's going to happen in the יובל *yovel*? He says,
he says לקוחות הן ומחזירין זה לזה ביובל *lakuchos hein umachzirin zeh
lazeh b'yovel*. Come the יובל *yovel*, they're going to have to put
it back into the, you know, the joint property of the estate
and then they're going to have to renegotiate how to split it
back out. I mean, one wonders how you can run society that
way. Right, I mean, it's hard enough when you actually have things
that are purchased, but here, in every single inheritance, everything is going
to have to ultimately always go reverting back, you know, through multiple
generations, no matter how many ways it's been inherited, inherited, and spread
out to other generations. Comes the יובל *yovel*, it all, everything is
considered a purchase, it all like reverts back and then it all
sort of like gets re-divided.
Maybe people would make an agreement from the outset that we're not
going to do the חשבון *cheshbon* again and we'll just assume that
it gets re-divided the way we had it before. But nevertheless, that's
his way of conceptualizing it. Okay, so ואי סלקא דעתך לאו קניין
הגוף דמי *v'is salka daitach lav kinyan haguf dami*, so besides the
hard part that now they're going to have to renegotiate how they
divide the land, if you were to hold that קניין פירות *kinyan
peiros* is not קניין הגוף *kinyan haguf*, especially by ביכורים *bikurim*, right,
this is the case of וזמן שיובל נוהג *v'zman she'yovel noheig*, and
if you're going to say maybe ואינו קורא *v'eino korei* anytime that
there's some sense of purchase, so לא משכחת דמייתי ביכורים אלא חד
בר חד עד יהושע בן נון *lo meshkachat d'maisi bikurim ela chad
bar chad ad Yehoshua bin Nun*. Nobody would ever bring ביכורים *bikurim*
unless there was a family that was only father, son, father, son,
no siblings going all the way back to יהושע בן נון *Yehoshua
bin Nun*. Because as soon as there had been one sibling, the
land therefore had been sold and divided, implicitly sold to the other
sibling, and then it would have to be, you know,
and every and then it would always have to go back to
the estate and then re-divide. So the only way something would not
be a קניין פירות *kinyan peiros*, a sale during the יובל *yovel*,
would be if there was never an inheritance that got divided, right?
So that's obviously absurd. So by the way, תוספות *Tosafos* has a
hard time because of the bottom line פסק *psak*. Because in the
bottom line פסק *psak*, you know, here it's not clear, do we
פוסק *pasken* רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, do we פוסק *pasken* ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish*? But assuming we פוסק *pasken* ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* that
קניין פירות *kinyan peiros* is לאו כקניין הגוף דמי *lav kekinyan haguf
dami*, right, תוספות *Tosafos* is bothered that we also seem to פוסק
*pasken* that you say אין ברירה *ein breira*. And therefore if you're
going to say אין ברירה *ein breira*, you're going to be back
to
this problem. So תוספות *Tosafos* says what's logical, which is that even
if in general you hold אין ברירה *ein breira*, that would not
go so far to say that, you know, and then when we
divided the land it was like I'll swap you my half in
the north for your half in the south, that would not go
so far to say that when the יובל *yovel* would come it
would all revert. revert. Like you can't run a society that way.
And the way תוספות conceptualizes it is that the תורה Torah only
says things that really start off as a sale and a purchase
revert. Something that is the dividing of a ירושה, yerusha, even though
conceptually, you're swapping your half for the other person's half, that would
not be something that would revert. So it would be possible to
hold קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף דמי kinyan perot lav kekinyan haguf
dami. and nevertheless things wouldn't revert. Okay,
anyway. Okay, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, קרא ומתניתא מסייעי לריש לקיש. Kra
Umatnita Mesaye'ei Le'reish Lakish. A פסוק and a ברייתא braita, supports ריש
לקיש. קרא במספר שני תבואות ימכר לך. Kra Bemispar Shnei Tevuot Yimkor
Lach. The פסוק that's talking about the יובל says that you figure
out the value of the field based on the number of years
of produce until the יובל. Now even though that's talking about how
to assess the fair price, it makes it sound like, you know,
כי מספר תבואות הוא מוכר לך ki mispar tevuot hu mocher lach
is basically more what, you know, the end of the פסוק is
more relevant, because it's saying effectively he's just selling you the years
of produce. So it frames the sale as effectively about the produce
and therefore seems to undercut the sense that you are considered to
be the real owner of the field. מתניתא, Matnita, a ברייתא, Baraisa
דתניא detanya ותני ברייתא, vetan baraita, בכור נוטל פי שנים בשדה החוזרת
לאביו ביובל, bechor notel pi shnayim besadeh hachozeret le'aviv beyovel, that a
בכור bechor gets two a double portion in a field that would
revert to the father in the יובל. Meaning, father sold the field
to somebody else. And then the father dies. Okay, so this that
field is going to come back in the יובל. When it comes
back in the יובל, does the בכור bechor get a double portion?
What's the question? The principle is that a בכור bechor gets a
double portion in things that are considered to be under the father's
control when the father dies, but not that are out of the
father's control. So for example, if there's an outstanding loan when that
loan gets paid, okay, the בכור bechor does not get a double
portion if it gets paid after the father dies, because it was
not under the father's control. So, when the father sold land during
the יובל, the fact that we say it is considered under the
father's control means that the person who has the ownership of that
field until the יובל, it's only considered a קניין הפירות kinyan haperot
which is not a קניין הגוף, he's not considered the owner, the
father even during this period is considered the owner, the other person
just has rights to the fruit. And since the father is the
owner, the בכור bechor gets the double portion. Okay, אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, נקטינן, naktinan, we take as the הלכה halacha
בעל בנכסי אשתו צריך הרשאה. ba'al benichsei ishto tzarich harsha'ah. This is
also seems to be part of the whole point of קניין פירות
לאו כקניין הגוף דמי. kinyan perot lav kekinyan haguf dami. If the
husband wants to go to court to argue on behalf of his
wife to defend his wife's interest in a field that he has
the קניין פירות, this is a נכסי מלוג nichsei melog and his
wife has the title, and his wife has the קניין הגוף. So
if he wants to do that, you're not allowed to, you know,
you need standing. You're not allowed to go ahead and argue for
somebody, represent somebody in court unless you are the person or you
have a הרשאה, harsha'ah, you basically have a type of a power
of attorney is essentially what the הרשאה harsha'ah is. Okay, so we
won't go into the details of that. So אביי Abaye says if
the husband wants to take somebody to court to defend his wife's
ownership of the field, he needs this הרשאה, harsha'ah, which proves that
he, the owner, the husband, is not considered to be the owner
of the field, קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף דמי. ולא אמרן אלא
דלא נחית אפירי, Velo amaran ela delo nachit apeiri, but that's only
if the court case is limiting itself to issues relating to the
title of the field. So for him to be considered to be
owner and have the title, he needs this power of attorney. אבל
נחית אפירי, Aval nachit apeiri, but if the debate is also about
the fruit, מיגו דמשתעי דינא אפירי migo demishtei dina apeiri משתעי דינא
אגופה, mishtei dina agufa, since he can defend his own interests as
far as the fruit is concerned because he owns the fruit, he
is entitled to defend his wife's interests as far as the ownership
of the land. All right, so that is again a proof that
general principle is קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף דמי. הדרן עלך השולח,
Hadran alach hashole'ach, that is the end of that פרק. perek. We
now continue the next פרק perek which continues with issues relating to
תיקון
עולם. tikkun olam. הניזקין שמין להן בעידית. Hanizakin, shamin lahen be'iddit. So,
when you assess somebody has damage done to them, a tort, like
you know, בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, somebody, you know, the cows went
in and grazed in his field or something of that nature, a
fire went and burned it down, etc. So he collects
from the person who owned the, you know, cow or set the
fire. And if
the person can either pay him in cash or מטלטלין, metaltelin, or
if he collects from land, then he would collect from what do
you call it, then he would collect from the best of the
person's fields. If the person has grade A land, grade B and
grade C, grade A is called עידית, iddit, the best, grade B
is called בינונית beinonit and grade C is זיבורית, ziborit, the worst.
You know, are these relative or objective? We'll see some of that
when we get to the גמרא. And the הלכה halacha here is
though he gets from the top quality land if he is coming
to collect from land. Okay. So all of this is going to
be because of תיקון עולם. tikkun olam. And as רש"י... Rashi... As
רש"י Rashi points out, people would much rather collect high quality land,
you know, which is much easier to sell than an equal dollar
value of low quality land which must be much harder to sell.
Okay, so therefore he's able to get one acre of top quality
land rather than ten acres of middle or low quality land. ובעל
חוב בבינונית, u'baal chov b'veinonis, when somebody has a—is a debtor and
comes to collect, so again, if you're not going to pay him
off in
cash or in chattel, and he's going to collect from land, so
he collects from middle quality land. ובעל חוב בבינונית, u'baal chov b'veinonis,
and that's also if he is collecting, you know, from the land
that has been sold to third parties. וכתובת אשה בזיבורית, u'kesuvas isha
b'ziboris,
and the כתובה kesuva of a wife, a man dies and his
wife is now coming to collect the כתובה kesuva amount and she's
got a lien on the property, she collects from the least quality,
from quality C. רבי מאיר אומר אף כתובת אשה בבינונית, Rabbi Meir
omer af kesuvas isha b'veinonis, even the כתובה kesuva is this B
quality.
Okay, and we'll see about this in the גמרא. אין נפרעין מנכסים
משועבדים במקום שיש נכסים בני חורין ואפילו הן זיבורית. Ein nifrahin mi'nechasim
meshubadim b'makom sheyesh nechasim bnei chorin va'afilu hen ziboris. One cannot collect
from property that has a lien on it when there is property
that is unencumbered even if they are of lesser quality. So let's
say you have the case of the debtor and he goes and
he comes to Reuven, who lent him the money. Now Reuven only
has left in his ownership C quality land, זיבורית. ziboris. But Reuven
sold some of his B stuff to, you know, Shimon and Levi
and Yehuda. The debtor can't say, "Well, look, as a debtor I'm
entitled to B quality land, I'm going to go to Shimon, Levi,
and Yehuda and exercise my liens." So the הלכה halacha is you're
not allowed to do that. Right, that's not fair to Shimon and
Levi and Yehuda. Even though you have liens and you can collect
from that property that Reuven sold them if Reuven can't pay up,
that's only once Reuven can't pay up. And if Reuven has property
in his own possession, that's called unencumbered, בני חורין, bnei chorin, then
you cannot go ahead and exercise your liens against these other people,
against the נכסים משועבדים. nechasim meshubadim. Okay, so and you have to
therefore accept the quality C land. אין נפרעין מנכסי יתומים אלא מן
הזיבורית. Ein nifrahin mi'nechasei yesomim ela min haziboris. Now when somebody
is—let's say Reuven owed me money and Reuven died and now I'm
going to collect from his heirs. So his heirs to some degree
are—it's similar to a case of a loan and now they're other
owners, they're new owners of that property, I have liens on that
property, so I really should be entitled to collect quality B, בינונית,
beinonis, but it's saying no, I'm going to have to get quality
C, זיבורית, ziboris, from the heirs. And all of this is because
of תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. אין מוציאין לאכילת פירות ולשבח קרקעות ולמזון
האשה והבנות מנכסים משועבדים מפני תיקון עולם. Ein motzi'in l'achilas peiros u'le'shevach
karka'os u'le'mezon ha'isha v'habanos mi'nechasim meshubadim mipnei tikkun olam. Now we're going
to a point of not of quality but of the right to
exercise liens. So somebody goes ahead and sells me land and it's—he
does it with אחריות, achrayus, which means that if somehow, you know,
it turns out that he did not have—he thought he had a
title to it or maybe he was lying, who knows, it winds
up that the land wasn't his, somebody else is—you know, it's recognized
somebody else had the title and the land has to go to
another person and they—they come and they take my land away from
me. And that's something that could happen. And I knew that that
was something that could happen, so I protected myself, I bought insurance,
which is called אחריות. achrayus. Okay, so now I went ahead and
I bought this land and I invested ten thousand dollars in planting
and sowing and whatever, and now I have this gorgeous garden. Okay?
So now it's worth twenty thousand dollars more. And comes along somebody
and has just proven in court that the guy who sold it
to me didn't really own it and he seizes this property. Okay,
with all of my wonderful improvements and my beautiful garden and so
on. Alright? So what this guy has to do, the guy who
seized it, he has to pay me back for my ten thousand
dollars of labor and investment. Okay? But now he—because like it's like
he hired me as a hired laborer retroactively. But now he takes
the land with its gorgeous garden that's now worth twenty thousand dollars
more. Where do I get my compensation for the ten thousand dollars
that I, you know, did not get reimbursed for, the improvement of
the land, plus the actual amount that I spent on the land
itself? Well, remember, I bought insurance. I have אחריות. achrayus. So I
can go back to the guy who sold it to me, Reuven,
and he—get him to pay me back for the base purchase price
of the land. But what about the improvement that I didn't get
reimbursed for? Okay, that extra ten thousand. So that is called אכילת
פירות, achilas peiros, אכילת פירות ושבח קרקעות, achilas peiros u'shevach karka'os, the
way I, you know, the fruit and the way I improved the
land and so on. So yes, I can go to Reuven, he
did give me insurance, but I cannot—but here's what plays out. For
the base purchase price of the land, if Reuven doesn't have any
property on him, I can go ahead and get property that Reuven
sold. I have liens against
Reuven's property. you know, for this loss. That's the insurance gave me
those liens. Okay, and that can be for the base amount, but
I cannot go to people ראובן Reuven sold his property to to
collect for the, you know, my lost improvements on the land, אכילת
פירות Achilas Peros and שבח קרקעות, Shevach Karkos, that I can only
collect from ראובן directly. And you might be able to figure out
the reason because purchasers of ראובן's lands don't know how to protect
themselves. The amount that פירות and שבח קרקעות Shevach Karkos will be
is indeterminate, so that amount, even if I have insurance, I can
only collect from ראובן directly.
Similarly, ולמזון האשה והבנות, u'l'mezon ha'isha ve'habanos, one of the things that
a wife is entitled to is when a husband dies, her widow,
this is in the כתובה Kesuvah and the daughters, can continue to
be supported by the estate. So, you know, the estate has to
pay for their upkeep. So can the widow and daughters get property
that was sold by the estate, that they have basically exercised liens
in order for their support? And the answer is no. It has
to be property held by the estate directly, not property that the
estate sold. Again, that would not be fair to the purchasers because
it's not determinate how much that's going to be. מפני תיקון העולם.
Mipnei Tikkun Olam. והמוציא מציאה לא ישבע מפני תיקון העולם, Ve'hamotzi metzia
lo yishava mipnei tikkun olam, something a little bit different. If somebody
finds a wallet and returns it to someone and the person says,
what do you mean? There was $100 in this wallet. The guy
says, no, I only found 50 dollars in it. He says, take
an oath that there was only 50 dollars and not a hundred.
So he does not have to take an oath because then you're
not, that's a תיקון העולם Tikkun Olam that we exempt him from
taking an oath, otherwise you do not get people returning the wallets.
Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Okay, we start with
the idea that when somebody is damaged, they collect quality A property
because of תיקון העולם, Tikkun Olam, עידית, Idis, if they're collecting from
actual real estate. מפני תיקון העולם Mipnei Tikkun Olam says the גמרא,
דאורייתא היא, De'oraisa hi, it's from the תורה, דכתיב מיטב שדהו ומיטב
כרמו ישלם, De'ksiv meitav sadehu u'meitav karmo yeshaleim,
that it says that when somebody sends out his animal and it
consumes in another field, he should pay the best of his field
and the best of his vineyard, which we're assuming to mean the
best of the field, the highest quality field and vineyard of the
person who is responsible for the damage. Okay, and we're assuming that
that's not just true about what's called שן ורגל, Shein ve'regal, you
know, those like when the animal eats and walks, but it's about
all cases of נזיקין. Nezikin. So it's learned out from a פסוק.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, לא
צריכא אלא לרבי ישמעאל. Lo tzricha ela l'Rabbi Yishmael. The reason that
it's תיקון העולם Tikkun Olam is according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
דאמר מדאורייתא בדניזק שיימינן. De'amar mide'oraisa bi'dnizak shamminan.
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says that the when it says the best
of his fields, it means the best of the fields of the
ניזק, Nizak, the damagee, not the מזיק, Mazik, the damager. So if
let's say the person being damaged, his subjective highest quality field was
really, you know, let's give them a score, was really, you know,
80 on a scale from 1 to 100. And the מזיק's Mazik
highest quality fields were, you know, were in the 90 to 100
range. So because, so when the ניזק Nizak comes to collect from
the fields of the מזיק, Mazik, the מזיק Mazik does not have
to give him his A quality, the 90 to 100 group, he
can give him from his B quality, the 80 group, because that
is parallel to the best quality land that the ניזק Nizak has.
Okay, so you collect from the best quality. How do you define
best? Based on me, the ניזק's Nizak best. So what for me
is the best of my quality of the fields that I own,
I can collect from comparable quality from the מזיק's Mazik field even
if they're not the best of his fields. Okay, that's בדניזק שיימינן.
Bi'dnizak shamminan. So that would be the תורה הלכה Torah Halacha and
therefore the רבנן Rabbanan switch it to say בדמזיק שיימינן Bi'dmazik shamminan
that I actually get to collect from the best quality of the
מזיק's Mazik field because you want to make even more of an
incentive for people to be careful to not let their animals go
out and damage, you know, to be an incentive against negligence. דתניא.
De'tanya. Okay, now. מפני תיקון העולם שיימינן בדמזיק. Mipnei tikkun olam shamminan
bi'dmazik. משמע להו מפני תיקון העולם שיימינן בדמזיק. Mashma lehu mipnei tikkun
olam shamminan bi'dmazik.
מאי רבי ישמעאל? Mai Rabbi Yishmael? What is the רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi
Yishmael position? Where do we see it? דתניא דתנו בברייתא. De'tanya de'tanu
be'Baraisa. מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם. Meitav sadehu u'meitav karmo yeshaleim. מיטב
שדהו של ניזק ומיטב כרמו של ניזק דברי רבי ישמעאל. Meitav sadehu
shel Nizak u'meitav karmo shel Nizak divrei Rabbi Yishmael.
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says the best of the fields of the
ניזק. Nizak. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says לא בא הכתוב אלא לגבות לנזיקין מן העידית. Lo ba hakasuv
ela ligvos li'nezikin min ha'idis. No, the תורה is coming to tell
you that when you are coming to collect for damages, you have
the right to collect, you know, the value, you can't exceed the
value of the damage, but in terms of which property you collect
from, you have the right to collect from the
highest quality property, וקל וחומר להקדש Ve'kal v'chomer l'hekdesh and certainly by
הקדש. Hekdesh. We'll worry about what that means in a minute. Okay,
so now we already know where the גמרא is going to end
up, that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is going to say it's the
highest quality as defined by what is subjectively the highest for the
ניזק, Nizak, for the damaged party. Okay, but right now that's not
what the ברייתא Baraisa sounds like. Right now the ברייתא sounds like
that if my... If my animal damages a field, let's say an
acre of ראובן *Reuven*'s field, I have to pay back for even
if it was ראובן *Reuven*'s quality C land, I have to pay
back for the best fields of ראובן *Reuven*. If ראובן *Reuven* had
A, B, and C quality and my animal goes and eats an
acre in C, I have to pay him back as if he
ate an acre in A. Okay, if that's what it sounds like
from רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*. מיטב שדהו *Meitav sadehu* of the ניזק
*nizak*, that that's that you're actually paying back as if he ate
the best of the damagee's field. All right, so it's not what
property you collect from but actually like like how much you're paying.
Okay, so לרבי ישמעאל אכלה שמנה משלם שמנה אכלה כחושה משלם שמנה
*L'Rabbi Yishmael achla shmena m'shalem shmena achla kchusha m'shalem shmena*?
Does this make sense according to רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*? When he
ate from the fat land, the good land A, he pays back
an acre of A. And if he ate from land C, he's
going to pay back an acre of A? Like that's not just.
That doesn't make sense. Okay, although that sounds like what רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Yishmael* is saying, we can't accept that. אמר רב אידי בר
אבין הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שאכלה ערוגה בין ערוגות *Amar Rav Idi
bar Avin hacha b'mai askinan k'gon she'achla aruga bein arugot*. No, no,
no, what happened was that it went, the animal went and it
ate a row of grapes. Okay, ולא ידעינן אי כחושה אכלה אי
שמנה אכלה *v'lo yadinan i kchusha achla i shmena achla*. So let's
say, you know, we don't know, I had like prize grapes, you
know, some of my grapes were prize grapes that were worth, you
know, ten thousand dollars a row and some were worth a thousand
dollars a row, and it, you know, and I would know it
if I looked at it, but now that the animal ate from
it, I don't know whether he ate from the ten thousand dollar
grapes or the one thousand dollar grapes. In that case, it's telling
you you pay for the best. So we're still thinking that רבי
ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* is saying you pay as if he ate the
best but in a case where there's a level of doubt, okay?
So, אי כחושה אכלה ידעינן משלם לה ממיטב *i kchusha achla yadinan
m'shalem leh m'meitav*.
In that case you pay from the best. אמר רבא אי ידעינן
דכחושה אכלה משלם כחושה *Amar Rava i yadinan d'kchusha achla m'shalem kchusha*.
Rava says that doesn't make sense because we won't allow a read
of this פסוק *pasuk* to violate general principles we have in monetary
matters. And we know that if the הלכה *halakha* was that if
we knew that he ate the worst, the thousand dollar grapes, he
would pay a thousand. If that's true, then השתא דלא ידעינן *hashta
d'lo yadinan*, now that we don't know if it was the thousand
dollar grapes or the ten thousand dollar grapes, משלם שמנה *m'shalem shmena*?
How could you suggest that because of this פסוק *pasuk* he's going
to pay the higher amount? That violates general legal principles we have:
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה *Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya*. The general legal principle
is is that if we don't know how much I owe you,
whether it was a thousand or ten thousand, you have the burden
of proof. So we have רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*'s statement that sounds
like... רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says clearly what the פסוק *pasuk* means
is, you know, the amount you figure out the amount that's owed
and then the question is what property you collect from, so the
תורה *Torah* is telling you collect from the best property of the
מזיק *mazik*. רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* sounds like he's saying how much
do you pay? As if he ate the best. But the גמרא
*Gemara* rejects this; that would be unjust to make you pay more
and it would even than was damaged and it would even be
unjust to make you pay in a case of doubt more than
could be proven. So what the גמרא *Gemara* is going to wind
up saying is that,
and we'll get to this tomorrow, is that רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*
says like we said earlier that no, רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* agrees
that the amount you pay is the amount that was damaged, but
rather than collecting from the top quality of the of the damager,
the damagee, you collect from what the damager owns that's comparable to
the top quality of the damagee. Okay, even though that is the
middle quality of the damager. That's going to be רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi
Yishmael*'s position and therefore the תיקון עולם *tikun olam* is to allow
you to actually go and be רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*'s position and
to collect from the top quality, the עידית *iddit* of the damager.